Guide to the Walter Huber Meyer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Huber Meyer papers
1912-1978
MS 1476
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12
(29 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, lecture notes, forest inventories, and research data, which document Walter Huber Meyer's study and teaching of forest valuation and mensuration and his work as a forestry consultant to the Crossett Company, the Fordyce Lumber Company, the J. Neils Lumber Company, and the Georgia-Pacific Company.
Meyer, Walter H. (Walter Huber)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Forestry Library, 1988 and 1991.
Scope and Contents
The Walter Huber Meyer Papers are composed of correspondence, reports, lecture notes, forest inventories, and research data, which document Meyer's work as a professor of forestry and a forestry consultant. They highlight Meyer's work for the Pacific Northwest Experiment Station, the Yale University School of Forestry, the Crossett Lumber Company, the Fordyce Lumber Company, the J. Neils Lumber Company, and the Georgia-Pacific Corporation and his research on forest valuation and forest mensuration in Arkansas and the Pacific Northwest. While the earliest materials in the papers date from 1912, the bulk of the papers reflect Meyer's work during the years he served as a member of the Yale Forestry School faculty, 1939-1963. The Yale Forestry Library transferred the Meyer Papers to the Manuscripts and Archives Department in 1988.
Meyer arranged his papers in binders by topics, which reflect various aspects of his career. The papers remain in these binders. The contents of the binders are more fully described in Meyer's index to his papers, which is in a separate volume in folder 1. The index, however, lists more materials than were transferred to the Manuscripts and Archives Department. Only volumes under the headings: Forest Experiment Station; Studies at Yale; Instruction; Yale Crossett Camp; J. Neils Lumber Camp; Fordyce Lumber Company; Crossett Lumber Company; Forest Utilization Economic Study; Georgia Pacific; and St. Croix are now in the Meyer Papers. The papers do not include material described in the index as Meyer's publications or files for his extra-curricular activities such as the American Forestry Association or the Society of American Foresters. Neither do the files contain any general correspondence or personal papers.
The Walter Huber Meyer Papers are arranged in the order outlined in Meyer's index. In the container list which follows folder titles are those used in the index or on the binder. Included in the folder title, in parentheses, is the Roman numeral-Arabic numeral code employed by Meyer to indicate his section and volume numbers. At the end of the listing there are four unnumbered volumes containing Crossett forest inventory statistics. Though some volumes contain correspondence the bulk of the material in the binders is reports and research data including charts and tables relating to forest management.
Biographical / Historical
Walter H. Meyer, 85, Harriman Professor Emeritus of Forest Management, died in New Haven on November 18, 1981, of an infection after an operation. He had been quite well and active until then; he had retired in 1963 after 24 years as a faculty member.
A native of New Haven born in 1896, Professor Meyer received B.A., M.F., and Ph.D. degrees from Yale, in 1919, 1922, and 1929, respectively. As an undergraduate mathematics major, he had been elected to Phi Beta Kappa in his junior year and to Sigma Xi as a senior. Following the completion of his master's program, he was granted an American-Scandinanvian Foundation Fellowship and studied at the Royal Institute of Forestry in Stockholm in 1922-1923.
Professor Meyer entered the U.S. Forest Service in 1923, on his return from Sweden, and served on the staff of the Northeastern Forest Experiment Station at Amherst, MA until 1926, when he was transferred to the Pacific Northwest Forest Experiment Station, Portland, OR. During his career in the Forest Service he did a number of studies of the mensuration, growth, and yield of such species as Douglas-fir, ponderosa pine, and red spruce that remain in use to this day.
Walt spent a leave in 1928-1929 at Yale doing the work that led to the first Ph.D. degree awarded under the aegis of an American forestry school. From 1936 to 1939, he was professor of forest management at the University of Washington. He returned to Yale to fill the vacancy left on the faculty by the retirement of Dean Graves.
His initial duties at Yale involved teaching forest economics and policy as well as statistics and forest mensuration. When Professor Herman Chapman retired in 1943, Meyer took over instruction in forest management and finance which he continued for the rest of his career. However, there was a hectic period during the resumption of instruction in 1945-1946 when he taught all of the courses listed here and also steered the resumption and relocation of the southern field instruction at Crossett, AR. Of all the many things that he did, there was nothing that brought more mutual pride and satisfaction to Walt and about 250 students than 17 spring-semester sessions at Crossett. Some of the students stayed in the western South and the others carried what they learned to many distant places. In this instruction and in his research, he pioneered in introducting many methods of mathematical analysis, now commonplace, into practical application in forest management.
His publications included five technical bulletins and other major publications of the U.S. Department of Agriculture and four bulletins in the Yale Forestry series. He was joint author, with H. H.Chapman, of two standard forestry textbooks published by McGraw-Hill Book Company: Forest Valuation (1947) and Forest Mensuration (1949).
While in the Pacific Northwest, he served as chairman of various committees and organizations, including the Puget Sound Section of the Society of American Foresters and the Forestry Committee of the Washington State Planning Council. He was chairman of the SAF Committee on Civil Service from 1942-1948 and a member of the SAF Accrediting Committee in 1948 to 1954. He was honored by election as a Fellow of the Society of American Foresters in 1959. He also served on the Board of Directors of the American Forestry Association from 1944 through 1952. He was for many years forestry consultant to the Crossett Company and the Fordyce Lumber Company in Arkansas, and the J. Neils Lumber Company in Washington and Montana; this relationship continued with the Georgia-Pacific Company after it acquired the Arkansas companies.
He is survived by his wife, Constance B. Meyer of Hamden, CT and a son, Walter, Jr., a Bureau of Land Management forester who lives at Eagle, ID, and by two grandchildren.
From: Yale Forest School News, vol. 70, no. 1.
Forest management; Forests and forestry -- Measurement; Forests and forestry -- Valuation; Forests and forestry -- Arkansas; Forests and forestry -- Montana; Forests and forestry -- Washington (State); Meyer, Walter H. (Walter Huber); United States. Forest Service; Crossett Lumber Company; Fordyce Lumber Company; Georgia-Pacific Corporation; J. Neils Lumber Company; Pacific Northwest Forest Experiment Station (Portland, Or.); Yale University. School of Forestry -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Index (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Forest Experiment Station
    - Pacific Northwest
      - Office manuscripts (II-2), 1927-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Forest types of Lewis County, Washington (II-3), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Contents of mensurational files (II-4), 1926-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Ponderosa pine management (II-5), 1933-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Douglas fir sample plots (II-6), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Growth of douglas fir and ponderosa pine (II-7), 1929-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Studies at Yale
    - Connecticut hardwood volume study (III-1), 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Volume-diameter ratio studies (III-2), 1944-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Loblolly pine yield study calculations (III-3), 1948-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Reconstructed sample plot tallies; Southern pine yield study (III-4) (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous calculations and tests (III-5), 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Survey of industrial forestry; study of earning capacities of wood-using industries (III-7), 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Russian forestry terms (III-8), 1932 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Finnish forestry terms (III-9), 1944 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Abstracts of European mensurational literature (III-10), 1928-1929 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Mensurational abstracts (III-11), 1925-1957 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Instruction
    - Forest valuation-lecture notes and materials (VI-13), 1940-1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Industrial forestry seminars (VI-15), 1955-1962 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Yale Crossett Camp
    - Forest management-southern camp manual (VII-1), 1953-1961 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Yale camp cruises (VII-2), 1946-1962 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Yale camp cruises (VII-3), 1951-1955 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Yale camp cruises (VII-4), 1956-1962 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Increment core summaries and analyses (VII-5), 1946-1962 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Timber management plans (VII-8), 1948-1958 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Inventory plans (VII-9), 1938-1962 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - J. Neils Lumber Company
    - Klickitat, Washington-general (VIII-1), 1938-1946 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Klickitat, Washington-general (VIII-2), 1947-1964 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Consulting forester reports (VIII-3), 1937-1960 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Klickitat, Washington-records, outside reports (VIII-4), 1936-1959 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Klickitat, Washington-records (VIII-5), 1938-1972 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Klickitat, Washington-records (VIII-6), 1945-1956 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Klickitat, Washington-records (VIII-7), 1937-1956 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Libby, Montana affairs (VIII-8), 1940-1960 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Kootenai cooperative sustained yield unit project (VIII-9), 1944-1947 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Kootenai cooperative sustained yield unit project (VIII-10), 1943-1948 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Libby, Montana-reports (VIII-11), 1941-1960 (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - Libby, Montana-reports (VIII-12), 1929, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Fordyce Lumber Company
    - General correspondence (IX-1), 1938-1963 (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - Fordyce records-part 1 (IX-2), 1948-1962 (Box 13, Folder 40)
    - Fordyce records-part 2 (IX-3), 1930-1961 (Box 13, Folder 41)
    - Fordyce records-part 3; annual reports (IX-4), 1942-1962 (Box 13, Folder 42)
    - Fordyce inventory (IX-5), 1943-1945 (Box 14, Folder 43)
    - Fordyce forest inventories (IX-6), 1953 (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - Fordyce forest inventory (IX-7), 1953-1955 (Box 14, Folder 45)
    - Fordyce forest inventory (IX-8), 1960-1964 (Box 14, Folder 46)
    - Fordyce forest inventory and management proposal (IX-9), 1953, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 47)
    - Consulting for reports (IX-10), 1943-1961 (Box 15, Folder 48)
  - Crossett Lumber Company
    - Crossett records (X-1), 1912-1962 (Box 15, Folder 49)
    - Crossett records (X-2), 1925-1962 (Box 15, Folder 50)
    - Crossett records (X-3), 1934-1961 (Box 15, Folder 51)
    - General correspondence (X-4), 1942-1962 (Box 16, Folder 52)
    - Consulting foresters reports; miscellaneous reports (X-5), 1943-1962 (Box 16, Folder 53)
    - 1949 reinventory and prior (X-6), 1912-1956 (Box 16, Folder 54)
    - 1959 reinventory (X-7), 1957-1961 (Box 16, Folder 55)
    - 1959 forest inventory and management proposal (X-8), 1949, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 56)
    - 1959 forest inventory-supplementary tables and data sheets (X-8A) (Box 17, Folder 57)
    - Aerial survey projects (X-9), 1948-1953 (Box 17, Folder 58)
    - Volume and taper studies (X-10), 1948-1953 (Box 17, Folder 59)
    - Southern pine volume studies (X-11), 1946-1961 (Box 17, Folder 60)
    - Hardwood volume studies (X-12), 1949-1957 (Box 18, Folder 61)
    - Volume studies (X-13), 1953-1962 (Box 18, Folder 62)
    - Special volume studies (X-14), 1953-1962 (Box 18, Folder 63)
    - Continuous forestry inventory (X-15), 1955-1964 (Box 18, Folder 64)
    - Control forties (X-16), 1940-1953 (Box 18, Folder 65)
    - Methods of cutting studies (X-17), 1946-1962 (Box 19, Folder 66)
    - Pine management intensification (X-18), 1952-1961 (Box 19, Folder 67)
    - Cutover land reports (X-19), 1934-1960 (Box 19, Folder 68)
    - Hardwood management (X-20), 1946-1961 (Box 20, Folder 69)
    - Union Bag-Camp negotiations (X-21), 1959-1961 (Box 20, Folder 70)
    - Annual reports of forestry division (X-22), 1941-1962 (Box 20, Folder 71)
    - Annual reports and brochures (X-23), 1943-1964 (Box 21, Folder 72)
  - Forest Utilization Economic Study
    - Collection of reports by WHM (XI-1), 1954-1960 (Box 21, Folder 73)
    - Forestry utilization economic study (XI-2), 1954-1962 (Box 21, Folder 74)
    - Revision of the forestry utilization economic study reports: 1958-original, 1959-duplicate (XI-3), 1958-1961 (Box 22, Folder 75)
    - Revision of the forestry utilization economic study reports: 1959-original (XI-3), 1958-1961 (Box 22, Folder 76)
    - Report revisions (XI-4), 1954-1960 (Box 22, Folder 77)
    - General correspondence and programs (XI-5), 1954-1960 (Box 22, Folder 78)
    - Log grades (XI-7), 1949-1955 (Box 23, Folder 79)
    - Pine-grade recovery studies (XI-8), 1954-1961 (Box 23, Folder 80)
    - Hardwood grade recovery (XI-9), 1954-1956 (Box 23, Folder 81)
    - Miscellaneous grade recovery studies (XI-10), 1923-1958 (Box 23, Folder 82)
    - Pine studies in the mill (XI-11), 1954-1961 (Box 24, Folder 83)
    - Log volumes and values; tree grade values (XI-12), 1954-1957 (Box 24, Folder 84)
    - Rates of production (XI-13), 1954-1956 (Box 24, Folder 85)
    - Costs (XI-14), 1952-1956 (Box 24, Folder 86)
    - Prices; poles and piling (XI-15), 1953-1961 (Box 25, Folder 87)
    - Sawtimber utilization committee (XI-16), 1960-1961 (Box 25, Folder 88)
  - Georgia Pacific
    - Period of adjustment; general (XII-1,2), 1962-1978 (Box 25, Folder 89)
    - Volumes studies-1963, 1964, 1966 (XII-3), 1963-1968 (Box 25, Folder 90)
    - Volume study-pine; volume study-hardwood (XII-4), 1966-1972 (Box 25, Folder 91)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence; special studies A (XII-5), 1964-1971 (Box 26, Folder 92)
    - Special studies B (XII-6), 1955-1972 (Box 26, Folder 93)
    - Inventory plans (XII-7), 1964-1973 (Box 26, Folder 94)
    - Crossett inventory reports (XII-8), 1963-1978 (Box 26, Folder 95)
    - Fordyce inventory reports (XII-9), 1966-1977 (Box 27, Folder 96)
    - Louisville inventory (XII-10), 1964-1972 (Box 27, Folder 97)
    - Source materials, Crossett inventory study (XII-11), 1912-1978 (Box 27, Folder 98)
  - St. Croix general (XIII-1), 1960-1969 (Box 27, Folder 99)
  - unnumbered
    - Crossett forest inventory, 1939, 1949 (Box 27, Folder 100)
    - Crossett forest inventory statistics-volume 1, 1939, 1949 (Box 27, Folder 101)
    - Crossett forest inventory statistics-volume 2, 1939-1949 (Box 28, Folder 102)
    - Crossett forest inventory statistics-volume 3, 1939-1949 (Box 28, Folder 103)
- Additional Material, 1923-1978; Accession 1994-M-049; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Diane E. Kaplan 1994 January
  Received from: Yale Forestry Library, 1991 Jan 28
  - Publications
    - Statistical Analysis in Timber Testing (I-unnumbered), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sustained Yield Possibilities and Practices in the Klickitat Unit, State of Washington (I-unnumbered), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Development and Application of Forest Inventories at Crossett and Fordyce, Arkansas (I-unnumbered), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Yields of Second Growth Spruce and Fir in the Northwest: original version (I-2), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Changing the Guard: Crossett to Georgia Pacific": notes only (unindexed), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Forest Experiment Station
    - Northeastern plus Miscellaneous (II-1), 1923-1925, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)